Guide to the New York Building Congress Records WAG.167
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Building Congress Records
1918-2017
1960-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
New York Building Congress
Anderson, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1940-
Draudt, Alanna
WAG.167
64 Linear Feet in 53 record cartons, 16 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 2 oversize flat boxes, and 2 shared folders.
82.9 Gigabytes in 13,034 computer files
The New York Building Congress (NYBC) is an association that brings together employers, labor unions, government agencies, engineers, architects, financiers, suppliers and others engaged in the construction industry in New York City. Founded in 1921, it now represents approximately 400 organizations, with a combined membership of over 250,000 skilled workers and professionals. The Congress engages in educational and lobbying activity, hosts public programs, and disseminates information on issues of concern to the industry. Additionally, the organization focuses on supporting sound public policy, promoting productive capital spending, encouraging public/private partnerships, and evaluating the implementation of major government projects in the construction sector. The collection consists of the administrative, general, and event files of the NYBC, as well as publications, photographs, and audio-visual materials produced by or for the organization. It documents the organization's role in establishing standards for construction through the Building Industry Practices Committee, as well as its important role in New York City legislative issues. The event files cover a variety of activities, from the lavishly produced Christmas shows and "Fun and Frolic" celebrations held from the 1930s through 1980s, to the conferences and issue-oriented forums that became a prominent feature of Congress activity in the 1990s and beyond.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the New York Building Congress, 1998. The accession numbers 1999.013, 1999.014 and NPA.2003.081 are associated with this gift. Additional material was donated in 2009, 2011, and 2012. The accession numbers 2009.021, 2011.015, 2012.011, and 2018.038 are associated with these materials.
Alanna Draudt donated materials in 2016 and 2018. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2016.028 and 2018.042.
Richard Anderson donated materials in 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.038.
Separated Materials
Periodicals were separated for cataloging by the Library.
Related Materials
Building Trades Employers Association Records (WAG 196)
Building Trades Oral History Project, Audio (OH 045)
The Tamiment Library also holds a substantial number of periodicals published by NYBC, including the Building Congress News, Metrobuild, and Edifice.
Historical Note
The New York Building Congress (NYBC) is an association that brings together employers, labor unions and federations, government agencies, engineers, architects, finaniers, suppiers and others engaged in the construction industry in New York City. Founded in 1921, it now has around 400 affiliated organizations, with a combined membership of over 250,000 skilled workers and professionals. The Congress engages in educational and lobbying activities, hosts public programs, and disseminates information of concern to the industry.
Shortly after the First World War, elements of the American building industry attempted to organize a national building congress. Although the planned national organization was never very active, the impulse was continued by city-wide groups. In New York City, the 47-member NYBC was organized in early 1921. Originally, membership was limited to organizations (labor unions, businesses, government agencies, etc.), but it was soon opened to individuals, and its early presidents were noted architects. On this broad basis, the NYBC united labor and employers, as well as members of the multitude of professions involved in all aspects of the building industry. One of the NYBC's key roles in its early years was to mediate between labor and management.
The NYBC issued a code of ethics for the building industry during its inaugural year, and remained actively involved in setting industry standards until the 1960s. The organization concerned itself with specific building practices; it commissioned research, published reports, lobbied, and spoke out on legislation and regulations pertaining to the industry. The NYBC took a leading role in the revision of the New York City Building Code in the 1960s and also lobbied on more general issues, such as the New York City charter revision of the late 1980s, the Westway project, and a variety of other development proposals for the city.
Over the years the organizational structure of the NYBC varied dramatically, as can be seen in the multitude of committees, subcommittees, councils, and boards listed in the inventory below. Nevertheless, some functions have remained consistent. From the beginning, the NYBC has regularly sponsored research, held conferences, presented awards to leaders in the industry, and hosted dinners and luncheons that have been addressed by some of New York's, and the nation's, most distinguished individuals.
Following the long presidencies of John J. Collins and Louis J. Coletti, the NYBC has been led by Richard T. Anderson since 1994. During this time, the Congress has frequently addressed legislative, regulatory, urban development, and political issues crucial to the industry. A recent Congress initiative was the establishment of the New York Building Foundation (NYBF), which undertakes industry research and philanthropic activities.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the administrative, general, and event files of the NYBC, as well as some publications, photographs and audio-visual materials produced by or for the organization. It documents the organization's role in establishing standards for construction through the Building Industry Practices Committee, as well as its important role in New York City legislative issues. The event files cover a variety of activities, from the lavishly produced Christmas shows and "Fun and Frolic" celebrations held from the 1930s through 1980s, to the conferences and issue-oriented forums that became a prominent feature of Congress activity in the 1990s and beyond.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into ten series, two of which have been further arranged into subseries. The contents of Series I are arranged by organizational hierarchy. Series II-IV and VI are arranged alphabetically. Series VII is arranged by format and then by date. Series VIII and X are unprocessed.
Series I: Minutes (1925-2010)
Series II: Administrative Records (1921-2010)
Series III: General Files (1918-2011)
Series IV: Events (1938-2010)
Series V: Oversized Materials (1947-2008)
Series VI: Photographs (1936-2008)
Subseries VI:A: Meetings (1947-1999)
Subseries VI:B: Events (1944-2008)
Subseries VI:C: Portraits (1936-1988)
Subseries VI:D: Site Photographs (1948-1974)
Subseries VI:E: Other Formats and Oversize (1943-1988)
Series VII: Audio-Visual Materials (1987-2004)
Subseries VII:A: Audiocassettes (1987-1997)
Subseries VII:B: Video (VHS) (2001-2004)
Series VIII: Unprocessed Materials (1985-2015)
Series IX. Archived Website
Series X. Richard T. Anderson Papers (1980-2015)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
A limited number of rolled photographs (approximately 15) are noted in the container list. Please consult Tamiment staff for access to these materials.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Building laws -- New York (State) -- New York; Building trades -- New York (State) -- New York; Westway (New York, N.Y.); Construction industry -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Coletti, Louis J.; Hennessey, John F.; 1989 Charter Revision Commission (New York, N.Y.); New York City Charter Revision Commission (1986-1988); Building Trades Employers' Association; Anderson, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1940-; Schaffner, Charles; New York Building Congress; Anderson, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1940-; Draudt, Alanna
- Series I: Minutes, 1925-2010
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Minutes, 1925-2010 consists of minutes of the Board of Governors, Board of Directors, Executive Committee, and other NYBC and NYBF committees.
  - Board of Governors (?), 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Governors, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Governors, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Governors, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Governors, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Board of Directors, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors, 2004-2007 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Board of Directors, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee, 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Executive Committee, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Executive Committee, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Executive Committee, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Executive Committee, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Executive Committee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Executive Committee, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Executive Committee, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Executive Committee, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Executive Committee, 2004-2007 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Executive Committee, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - New York Building Foundation: Board of Governors, 1999-2007 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - New York Building Foundation: Board of Governors, 2008-2010 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - New York Building Foundation: Executive Committee, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Membership Committee, 1954-1958 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Membership Committee, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Communications and Membership Committee, 2003-2007 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Council of Presidents, 2003-2007 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Architects Leadership Council, 2000-2007 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Economic Development Committee, 2000-2007 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Energy Committee, 1999-2007 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Public Building Committee, 2002-2007 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Transportation and Infrastructure Committee, 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Transportation and Infrastructure Committee, 2005-2007 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Series II: Administrative Records, 1921-2010
  Series II: Administrative Records, 1921-2010 contains memos, reports, and other records relating to the management of the NYBC. Much material is available on the Board of Directors and the Council of Presidents. The many different committees of the NYBC are documented here, especially the Building Industry Practices Committee, the Executive Committee and the Membership Committee. Committee files include agendas, correspondence, and meeting packets. Although none of the records are without gaps, the best coverage is of the 1950s-1990s. President Richard T. Anderson's chronological file consists mostly of his correspondence, but also includes memos, reports, and other documents.
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Energy, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Homeless, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Affordable Housing Task Force, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Alert Bulletins, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Alert Bulletins, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Alert Bulletins, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Alert Bulletins, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President), 1994-1996, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 52a)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jan-Apr 1998 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, May-Dec 1998 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jan-Jun 1999 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jul-Dec 1999 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jan-Apr 2000 (Box 1A, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, May-Aug 2000 (Box 1A, Folder 2)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jun-Sep 2002 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Oct-Dec 2002 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jan-Jun 2003 (Box 1A, Folder 5)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jul-Dec 2003 (Box 1A, Folder 6)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jan-May 2004 (Box 1A, Folder 7)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jun-Oct 2004 (Box 1A, Folder 8)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Jun-Sep 2005 (Box 1A, Folder 9)
  - Anderson, Richard T. (President): Chronological File, Oct-Dec 2005 (Box 1A, Folder 10)
  - Annual Reports, 1956-1962 (Box 1A, Folder 11)
  - Annual Reports, 1963-1967 (Box 1A, Folder 12)
  - Annual Reports, 1987-1990 (Box 1A, Folder 13)
  - Annual Reports, 1995-1997 (Box 1A, Folder 14)
  - Annual Reports, 1998-2008 (Box 1A, Folder 15)
  - Annual Review, 1986-1988 (Box 1A, Folder 16)
  - Apprenticeship Commission, 1922, Undated (Box 1A, Folder 17)
  - Apprenticeship Commission: Closing Exercises, 1925-1931 (Box 1A, Folder 18)
  - Apprenticeship Committee, 1977 (Box 1A, Folder 19)
  - Arbitration Committee, 1924 (Box 1A, Folder 20)
  - Arbitration Committee, 1927 (Box 1A, Folder 21)
  - Architects Leadership Council, 2005 (Box 1A, Folder 22)
  - Architects Leadership Council, 2006 (Box 1A, Folder 23)
  - Architects Leadership Council, 2007-2010 (Box 1A, Folder 24)
  - Architects Leadership Council: Agendas, 2000-2007 (Box 1A, Folder 25)
  - Ballots and Proxies, 1929-1949 (Box 1A, Folder 26)
  - Ballots and Proxies, 1950-1977 (Box 1A, Folder 27)
  - Ballots and Proxies, 1994 (Box 1A, Folder 28)
  - Ballots and Proxies, 1995 (Box 1A, Folder 29)
  - Bicentennial Committee, 1974 (Box 1A, Folder 30)
  - Board of Directors, 1956-1957 (Box 1A, Folder 31)
  - Board of Directors, 1959 (Box 1A, Folder 32)
  - Board of Directors, 1960-1961 (Box 1A, Folder 33)
  - Board of Directors, 1967-1971 (Box 1A, Folder 34)
  - Board of Directors, 1973-1975 (Box 1A, Folder 35)
  - Board of Directors, 1977 (Box 1A, Folder 36)
  - Board of Directors, 1978 (Box 1A, Folder 37)
  - Board of Directors, 1979 (Box 1A, Folder 38)
  - Board of Directors, 1980 (Box 1A, Folder 39)
  - Board of Directors, 1981 (Box 1A, Folder 40)
  - Board of Directors, 1982 (Box 1A, Folder 41)
  - Board of Directors, 1983 (Box 1A, Folder 42)
  - Board of Directors, 1984 (Box 1A, Folder 43)
  - Board of Directors, 1985 (Box 1A, Folder 44)
  - Board of Directors, 1986 (Box 1A, Folder 45)
  - Board of Directors, 1987 (Box 1B, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors, 1988 (Box 1B, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors, 1989 (Box 1B, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors, 1990 (Box 1B, Folder 4)
  - Board of Directors, 1991 (Box 1B, Folder 5)
  - Board of Directors, 1992 (Box 1B, Folder 6)
  - Board of Directors, 1993 (Box 1B, Folder 7)
  - Board of Directors, Jan-Jun 1994 (Box 1B, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors, Jul-Dec 1994 (Box 1B, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors, 1995 (Box 1B, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors, 1996 (Box 1B, Folder 11)
  - Board of Directors, 1999 (Box 1B, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors, 2000 (Box 1B, Folder 13)
  - Board of Directors, 2001 (Box 1B, Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors, 2002 (Box 1B, Folder 15)
  - Board of Directors, 2007 (Box 1B, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors, 2008 (Box 1B, Folder 17)
  - Board of Directors, 2010 (Box 1B, Folder 18)
  - Board of Directors: Agendas, 1981-1985 (Box 1B, Folder 19)
  - Board of Directors: Agendas, 1999-2007 (Box 1B, Folder 20)
  - Board of Directors: Financial, 1979-1982 (Box 1B, Folder 21)
  - Board of Directors: Membership, 1980-1982 (Box 1B, Folder 22)
  - Board of Directors: Membership Directory, 2009 (Box 1B, Folder 22a)
  - Board of Directors: Nominations, 1989-1992 (Box 1B, Folder 23)
  - Board of Directors: Restructuring, 1978 (Box 1B, Folder 24)
  - Board of Governors, 1955-1957 (Box 1B, Folder 25)
  - Board of Governors, 1958-1959 (Box 1B, Folder 26)
  - Board of Governors, 1960-1964 (Box 1B, Folder 27)
  - Board of Governors, 1967-1968 (Box 1B, Folder 28)
  - Board of Governors, 1974-1976 (Box 1B, Folder 29)
  - Board of Governors, 1978 (Box 1B, Folder 30)
  - Board of Governors, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Governors, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Building Industry Leadership Council, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Building Industry Leadership Council: Research Institute Subcommittee, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Publications File, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Alternate Estimates, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Alternate Estimates, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Balancing and Testing of HVAC Systems, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Bidding Documents, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Blueprints, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Change Orders, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Change Orders, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Change Orders, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Change Orders, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Change Orders, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Change Orders, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Completion of a Building, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Completion of a Building, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Completion of a Building, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Coordination of Mechanical and Electrical Trades, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Coordination of Mechanical and Electrical Trades, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Coordination of Mechanical and Electrical Trades, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Coordination of Mechanical and Electrical Trades, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Guarantee Periods, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Guarantee Periods, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Guarantee Periods, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Holiday Practices in Offices, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Holiday Practices in Offices, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Holiday Practices in Offices, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on "Or Equal" Clause, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on "Or Equal" Clause, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on "Or Equal" Clause, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on "Or Equal" Clause, 1964-1969 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Owner Prepurchased Equipment, 1960-1962, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Paints and Colors, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Paints and Colors, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Paints and Colors, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Prequalification of Subcontractors, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Prequalification of Subcontractors, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Prequalification of Subcontractors, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Prints and Specifications, 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Responsibility for Coordination and Installation of Work, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Responsibility for Design and Installation of Building Construction, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Responsibility for Design and Installation of Building Construction, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Responsibility on Construction Jobs, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Responsibility on Construction Jobs, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Retained Percentages, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Shop and Installation Drawings, 1955-1956, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Temporary Heat, Light, and Power, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Building Industry Practices Committee: Subcommittee on Test Boring Information, 1960-1965 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Building Trades Agreements and Expiration Dates, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Business/Labor Coalition for New York, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Certificate of Incorporation: New York Building Congress, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 55)